[Music]
the generation that changed the world is
now changing the face of retirement a
generation who embraced life now
Embraces
lifestyle achieving a comfortable Secure
Retirement has been a dream of Canadians
for decades but Baby Boomers approach
retirement age the definition of
retirement is
[Music]
changing and as people change their
retirement goals the fundamentals of
saving for retirement are changing too
the coming generation of retirees will
face different yet greater Financial
challenges than ever
before Boomers like no other generation
are challenging conventional retirement
thinking we want to protect our assets
but at the same time we want them to
grow as Boomers we're less willing to
curb our spending habits or give up our
lifestyles to
retire so what worries us when we think
about retirement planning manual life
Investments ask Canadian
Boomers what are your biggest concerns
When approaching
retirement topping the list are
outliving retirement savings inflation
and Market
volatility today Canadians are living
longer than ever
before a couple now 65 years old has a
94% chance of one partner living to age
80 and a 63% chance of living to age 90
that means needing to fund your
retirement for up to 30
years I don't know if I got enough or
not that's to be honest I hope I'm
Diversified enough inflation also has a
major impact on your retirement savings
if the inflation rate is a approximately
2% what you can buy for $11,000 today
will only buy you
$552 worth of goods in 30 years time
that means $100 worth of groceries today
will cost you
$150 in 20 years and $180 in 30
years and again the hardest part is
trying to figure out what to do about it
is you know how much how much am I going
to need you don't know what inflation's
going to be uh uh what the cost of
living what's going to happen to the
cost of living so uh It's Tricky
unpredictable market conditions are also
a source of retirement concern and we
see it in the news all the
time the economy is at a stage now where
is it going to go and where our our RSP
is going to go uh should we be defensive
about them all of these factors are
legitimate concerns for Canadian Boomers
now preparing for or entering
retirement leading Canadian Financial
expert Moshe meski recently identified
another critical factor that can affect
a retirement portfolio the retirement
risk Zone the retirement risk zone is
the period just before and after
retirement when your portfolio is most
vulnerable to market downturns the
retirement risk Zone ATT atts to
describe the time period before
retirement and within 5 or 10 years
after retirement where a loss in the
stock market or a fall in the value of
their Investments can have a
disproportionate effect on the amount of
income that they can withdraw in
retirement it's a risk Zone it's one of
the risks that people face in retirement
and they have to manage that risk let's
examine why you're at greater risk from
stock market declines near or at
retirement compared to when you're
saving for retirement when you're in the
saving phase the order or sequence of
your investment returns is less
important provided you stay invested and
ride out the rough patches for example
if you received a return of 7% one year
then minus 133% the next year then 27%
the year after you earn an average 7%
return on your investment in fact if the
sequence of these returns changes and
the minus 13% return comes first your
outcome would still be the same an
average return of
7% however if you're in the retirement
risk Zone experiencing poor market
returns early in retirement can
significantly reduce your retirement
savings and have an impact on whether
they will last throughout your
retirement the reason is that your
portfolio may not have the time to
recover the way it could for a younger
investor even if the market does Rebound
another reason is that in retirement
you're withdrawing money from your nest
EG as income withdrawing money from
Investments that are already suffering
losses from the markets May mean that
you're depleting your declining
investment much more quickly and could
run out of money much sooner than you
expected let's explore this further
using the numbers from our previous
example say someone retired at age 65
with
$100,000 and plan to withdraw 9% of
their savings each year as income assume
they were somehow able to receive a
consistent 7% return every year on their
investment their money could last for 21
years until they were
86 let's look at this again but this
time the retiree earns 7% the first year
27% the second year minus 133% the third
year and so on in this order throughout
retirement the average return is still
7% but this time due to a couple of good
years in a row their money actually
lasts an additional 3 years until age 89
if we change the sequence of returns
again so that they earn 7% then minus
13% and then 27% in this order
throughout retirement the average return
is still 7% but now this person's
portfolio is depleted by age 83 6 years
earlier than if they'd had the good
returns 2 years in a row 6 years earlier
all because a retiree had The Misfortune
of suffering Market losses in the wrong
order isn't retirement the time to stop
worrying about your Investments income
inflation and the market ups and
downs that's why manual life Investments
created income Plus
[Music]
income plus offers investors the
opportunity of predictable sustainable
and potentially increasing income
regardless of how the markets perform to
give you an idea of how income plus
Works let's look at an
example Bob is age 65 retired and a
conservative investor with $200,000 in
retirement savings Bob needs a
predictable sustainable income for his
retirement
and to help him keep ahead of inflation
his investment needs to take advantage
of the growth potential of the markets
but Bob can't afford to lose his
retirement savings if markets decline he
needs a guarantee something that helps
protect his investment from losses and
offers growth potential income plus
allows Bob to take out 5% of his
Investments every year as retirement
income for a minimum of 20 years in
Bob's case 5% of his $200,000 investment
would be $10,000 per year with income
plus Bob's $10,000 income is guaranteed
even if the markets decline his
retirement income will not drop below
$10,000 for the entire length of the
investment contract but if the markets
grow so does Bob's guaranteed income
let's look at how income plus Works in
both declining and growing Market
scenarios looking first at a worst case
scen scenario let's say that the market
suffered an extreme decline for a long
period of time if Bob had invested his
$200,000 in the markets without the
protection of income plus his market
value would hit Zero by year
16 but with income plus Bob can continue
to receive his annual $10,000 income for
the entire 20-year length of the
contract income plus protected Bob from
a serious decline in the market but what
happens if the markets are strong Bob
invests his $200,000 and withdraws his
guaranteed $10,000 Pere income he does
this again after year 2 and year three
the markets do well and at the end of
the third year Bob's original $200,000
investment has grown and that's where an
interesting feature of income plus kicks
in income plus locks in that market
growth and now Bob's guaranteed income
increases to 5% of that higher market
value and this higher income will be
paid for 20 more years income plus can
lock in Bob's investment growth and
reset his income to a higher value every
3 years for 30 years that's 10 resets in
total these resets only occur if the
markets have risen over the 3-year
period if the markets have gone down in
the 3-year period a reset doesn't occur
the guaranteed income simply remains at
the previously locked in
[Music]
amount the resets which take advantage
of market growth are a great way to help
Bob ensure his guaranteed annual income
Rises and keeps Pace with inflation
let's examine another unique way income
plus can help meet retirement goals
Carol age 55 is 10 years away from
retirement and has saved $100,000
Carol needs significant growth in her
portfolio to help her retire comfortably
but if the markets aren't strong during
the next 10 years Carol's portfolio
won't have the time to recover and grow
before her retirement Carol invests
$100,000 in income plus but doesn't plan
to draw income until she retires 10
years from now for every year that she
doesn't draw income in the first 10
years income plus will add a 5% bonus to
Carol's
investment that means regardless of what
the markets have been doing income plus
will guarantee that Carol's $100,000
initial investment will grow 5% every
year for 10 years to
$150,000 that's a 50% increase amazingly
that's Carol's minimum case scenario it
assumes that the markets have been
negative for the entire 10-year period
let's see what happens if the markets
have been positive in that 10-year time
period Carol invests her $100,000 in
income plus she's 10 years away from
retirement and doesn't plan to withdraw
income until she retires manual lifee
adds the 5% bonus to her investment for
each year that she doesn't withdraw
income for the first 10 years but in
this scenario by the end of year three
the markets have grown and income plus
locks in that market growth Carol still
receives her 5% annual bonus but it's
now based on the new locked in value
these resets occur every 3 years in this
scenario another reset occurs in year
six but 3 years later at the time of the
next potential reset in year 9 say the
markets have declined with income plus
Carol is unaffected the reset that
occurred in year six locked in the high
point in the Market at that time and her
yearly 5% bonus continues at the amount
locked in at year six by the end of year
10 Carol can be ready to retire and her
nest EG has grown considerably with
income
plus income plus is flexible if for some
reason Carol needed to draw income
earlier she could easily access her
money in this case she would receive the
5% bonus for the years without any
withdrawal but there would be no bonus
in the year that she withdrew income not
only can manual life income Plus offer
investors the stability of a guaranteed
income but it offers the security of a
relationship with a well-respected
global
organization manual life has received
the rare and prestigious AAA rating from
standard and
pores a competitive advantage of working
with manual life Investments is its
ability to attract the best fund
managers available managers known for
flexible Solutions and Industry
success income plus offers predictable
sustainable and potentially increasing
income regardless of how the markets
[Music]
perform for more information on income
plus talk to your financial advisor or
visit
www.man incom plus.cc
[Music]